

209 N 9th Street, Apt. 3B, Philadelphia, PA 19107, USA

🛮 (+1) 408-772-0602 | 🗷 danh@dnguyen.io | 🐔 www.dnguyen.io | 🖸 dnguyen85 | 🛅 dnguyen85

Summary.

Final-year PhD candidate with 7 years' experience in research and development of hardware, software, and system components for modern wireless communication and networking systems. Fluent in embedded / FPGA development, C, Python, Matlab, and web frameworks (HTML, CSS, JS). Currently seeking full-time opportunities in the general areas of mobile computing and networking.

Education

Drexel University Philadelphia, PA

Ph.D. IN ELECTRICAL ENGINEERING (ADVISORS: K. R. DANDEKAR, N. KANDASAMY)

2009-Exp. 4/2017

Thesis: "Agile Spectrum Sharing Wireless Systems using Software Radios and Reconfigurable Antennas"

Drexel University Philadelphia, PA

M.S. IN COMPUTER ENGINEERING

2009-2014

Hands-on experience in computer architecture, hardware/software co-design, and telecommunications

Drexel University Philadelphia, PA

B.S. IN COMPUTER ENGINEERING

2006-2009

Graduated Summa Cum Laude, GPA: 3.96

Skills

Operating Systems Unix / Linux (proficient), Windows, MAC OS

Programming C / Python / Matlab (proficient), Java / C++ / C# (intermediate), PHP, HTML / CSS, Javascript

Libraries NumPy / Jupyter / Matplotlib / Pandas (Python), GNU Radio (C++), lwlP / mac80211 (C), Unity, Vuforia AR

Hardware Xilinx & Altera FPGA platforms (proficient), VHDL, Verilog, Xilinx System Generator, Modelsim

Version Control Git (proficient), Mercurial, SVN

Web Framework Node.JS with Express & MongoDB, Parse Server (mobile backend), Python Flask with MySQL, Drupal CMS

Wireless Standards IEEE 802.11a/g/n, 802.11ac, 802.11ad, LTE-A, LTE Direct, WiMAX, MIMO, mmWave

Other Skills Vim, Tmux, Terminal Shell (Bash / Zsh), Latex, Markdown, Pandoc, Microsoft Office, Inkscape, GIMP

Experience

Drexel Wireless System Laboratory

Philadelphia, PA

GRADUATE RESEARCH FELLOW

9/2009-Present

- Led the development of a mobile augmented reality framework based on Unity game engine & Vuforia (frontend), with Parse & Python middleware (backend), to visualize and control RF transmissions in wireless networks in real time. See [C2,5,7] for publications. Demo video: http://beamviewer.io
- Designed and implemented a **synchronous directional wireless architecture** that leverages time synchronization and dynamic antenna directionality to perform autonomous, machine learning-based beamsteering for optimizing network throughput. Built a real-time system prototype on the WARP software-defined radio platform. Four publications [C3,4,7; W1] and a patent [P3]
- Developed an **FPGA-based software-defined radio testbed** for dynamic spectrum access research in wireless small cells, leveraging a frequency-agile frontend for flexible spectrum access. One publication [C8]
- Implemented a real-time, protocol-aware reactive jammer using GNU Radio and the low-cost USRP N210 software radio platform. Three publications [C9,10,12] and a patent [P1]
- Co-developed a reconfigurable baseband hardware IP for scalable ultra wide-band OFDM processing. Implemented VHDL RTL modules to interface the baseband pipeline with high-speed (1GSPS) ADC and DAC frontends. Verified hardware designs using Modelsim and Xilinx Chipscope. Two publications [C11,13]
- Gained working knowledge of modern wireless communication systems: OFDM, CDMA, LTE, and WiMAX
- Developed and maintained the lab website at http://wireless.ece.drexel.edu

InterDigital Communications, Inc.

King of Prussia, PA 6/2013–6/2014

RESEARCH INTERN - VIDEO OVER WIRELESS

- Optimized video streaming over WiFi networks leveraging IEEE 802.11e QoS support for traffic access categories
- Implemented a control algorithm for network-assisted rebuffering prevention through QoS elevation of distressed video streams
- Prototyped the experimental WiFi video delivery system using OpenWRT (on commercial routers) with modified Linux 802.11 drivers (mac80211 and n180211 modules), and DASH video clients

Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, Drexel University

Philadelphia, PA

TEACHING ASSISTANT

2009-2014

· Taught lectures and lab sessions on Matlab, digital logic design, Java programming, and embedded systems

Freedom Rings Partnership

Philadelphia, PA

WEB DEVELOPER

8/2012-8/2013

• Developed in Drupal CMS features for the Freedom Rings Partnership's KEYSPOT website (https://www.phillykeyspots.org). Responsible for static pages, news and blog posting workflow, training materials repository and search functionality, E-Learning portal, and KEYSPOT finder

MediaTech, Inc. (Vietnam)

Hanoi, Vietnam

TECHNICAL CONSULTANT

1-5/2012

- Designed and implemented a proof-of-concept PBX phone system for live-broadcast TV interactive games based on Asterisk
- Performed system latency tests using landline, cellular, and SIP-based soft phones

Drexel High Performance Computing Laboratory

Philadelphia, PA

RESEARCH ASSISTANT (ADVISOR: J. JOHNSON)

6-12/2009

- Investigated performance bottlenecks of static auto-tuning software (ATLAS and OSKI) in sparse matrix-vector multiplication
- Analyzed and tested a lab-built Multiply-Accumulate (MAC) hardware design on FPGA using Xilinx ISE Suite

Motorola Inc. - Home & Network Mobility Division (now ARRIS Group, Inc.)

Horsham, PA

SOFTWARE ENGINEER CO-OP

3/2008-6/2009

- Developed C++ features for the thin client software layer of set-top boxes to enhance digital video recording (DVR). Debugged and improved device drivers for external mass storage devices (eMSD) to handle DVR's external hard drive configuration process
- Implemented the System Test Program (STP) framework for automation of all design validation tests in the group

SAP America, Inc.

Newtown Square, PA

R/3 System Administrator Co-op

3-9/2007

• Provided R/3 basis technical support for SAP systems used for demo, training, and consulting purposes

Publications

CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS

[C1] Enhancing Blind Interference Alignment with Reinforcement Learning

S. Begashaw, **D. H. Nguyen**, K. R. Dandekar

Proc. of IEEE Global Communications Conf. (GLOBECOM '16 - to appear), 2016

- [C2] Demo: WiART Visualize and Interact with Wireless Networks using Augmented Reality D. H. Nguyen, J. Chacko, L. Henderson, A. Paatelma, H. Saarnisaari, N. Kandasamy, K. R. Dandekar Proc. of 22nd Annu. Intl. Conf. on Mobile Computing and Networking (ACM MobiCom '16), 2016
- [C3] Enabling Synchronous Directional Channel Access on SDRs for Spectrum Sharing Applications
 D. H. Nguyen, A. Paatelma, H. Saarnisaari, N. Kandasamy, K. R. Dandekar
 Proc. of ACM Intl. Workshop on Wireless Network Testbeds, Experimental Eval., and Characterization (WiNTECH '16), 2016
- [C4] Demo: Enhancing Indoor Spatial Reuse through Adaptive Antenna Beamsteering (WinCool Best Demo Award)
 D. H. Nguyen, A. Paatelma, H. Saarnisaari, N. Kandasamy, K. R. Dandekar
 Proc. of ACM Intl. Workshop on Wireless Network Testbeds, Experimental Eval., and Characterization (WiNTECH '16), 2016
- [C5] BeamViewer: Visualization of Dynamic Antenna Radiation Patterns using Augmented Reality
 D. H. Nguyen, L. Henderson, J. Chacko, C. Sahin, A. Paatelma, H. Saarnisaari, N. Kandasamy, K. R. Dandekar
 Proc. of IEEE Conf. on Computer Communications Workshops (INFOCOM WKSHPS '16), 2016
- [C6] Experimental Evaluation of a Reconfigurable Antenna System for Blind Interference Alignment S. Begashaw, J. Chacko, N. Gulati, D. H. Nguyen, N. Kandasamy, K. R. Dandekar

- Proc. of IEEE Wireless and Microwave Technology Conf. (WAMICON '16), 2016
- [C7] Wireless Communications Engineering and Cybersecurity Education via Augmented Reality C. Sahin, D. H. Nguyen, S. Begashaw, B. Katz, J. Chacko, L. Henderson, J. Stanford, K. R. Dandekar *Proc. of IEEE Frontiers in Education Conf. (FIE '16)*, 2016
- [C8] Leveraging an Agile RF Transceiver for Rapid Prototyping of Small-Cell Systems D. H. Nguyen, M. Rauhanummi, H. Saarnisaari, N. Kandasamy, K. R. Dandekar *Proc. of IEEE Vehicular Technology Conf. (VTC-Fall '15)*, 2015
- [C9] Wireless Cybersecurity Education via a Software Defined Radio Laboratory C. Sahin, D. Nguyen, J. Chacko, K. R. Dandekar *Proc. of IEEE Frontiers in Education Conf. (FIE '15)*, 2015
- [C10] A Real-Time and Protocol-Aware Reactive Jamming Framework Built on Software-Defined Radios D. Nguyen, C. Sahin, B. Shishkin, N. Kandasamy, K. R. Dandekar *Proc. of ACM Workshop on Software Radio Implementation Forum (SRIF '14)*, 2014
- [C11] FPGA-Based Latency-Insensitive OFDM Pipeline for Wireless Research J. Chacko, C. Sahin, D. Nguyen, D. Pfeil, N. Kandasamy, K. R. Dandekar *Proc. of IEEE High Performance Extreme Computing Conf. (HPEC '14)*, 2014
- [C12] Real-Time, Channel-Aware Reactive Jamming in 802.11 Networks
 D. Nguyen, B. Shishkin, C. Sahin, D. Dorsey, N. Kandasamy, K. Dandekar
 Proc. of 2013 Wireless @ Virginia Tech Annu. Symp. 2013
- [C13] SDC Testbed: Software Defined Communications Testbed for Wireless Radio and Optical Networking
 B. Shishkin, D. Pfeil, D. Nguyen, K. Wanuga, J. Chacko, J. Johnson, N. Kandasamy, T. P. Kurzweg, K. R. Dandekar
 Proc. of Intl. Symp. on Modeling and Optimization in Mobile, Ad Hoc, and Wireless Networks (WiOPT '11), 2011

WORKING PAPERS (Unpublished)

[W1] LinkPursuit: An Adaptive Pursuit Learning Method to Mitigate Small-Cell Interference through Directionality D. H. Nguyen, A. Paatelma, H. Saarnisaari, N. Kandasamy, K. R. Dandekar Submitted (unsuccessfully) to ACM MobiCom '16. Under revision, 2016

PATENT / PATENT APPLICATIONS

- [P1] Real-Time, Channel-Aware Reactive Jamming in Wireless Networks
 B. Shishkin, D. H. Nguyen, C. Sahin, K. R. Dandekar, N. Kandasamy, D. J. Dorsey
 US Patent No. 9,531,497. Issued December 27, 2016
- [P2] Beam Visualization and STEM Education using Augmented Reality
 K. R. Dandekar, C. Sahin, L. J. Henderson, D. H. Nguyen, J. J. Chacko, X. R. Rey
 US Provisional Patent Application No. 62/403,415. Filed October 3, 2016
- [P3] An Adaptive Pursuit Learning Method to Mitigate Small-Cell Interference through Directionality D. H. Nguyen, A. Paatelma, H. Saarnisaari, N. Kandasamy, K. R. Dandekar US Provisional Patent Application No. 62/402,671. Filed September 30, 2016

TECHNICAL REPORTS (Available at http://wireless.ece.drexel.edu)

- [T1] Radio Frequency Coordination at the Democratic National Convention D. H. Nguyen, M. Jacovic, I. Rasheed, K. R. Dandekar *Tech. Rep. No. 1, Drexel Wireless Systems Laboratory, 2016*
- [T2] Real Time Feature Detection and Threat Analysis with USRP SDR B. Shishkin, D. Nguyen, C. Sahin, C. Miller Tech. Rep. No. 2, Drexel Wireless Systems Laboratory, 2012

Honors & Awards

2016	WinCool Best Demo, ACM WiNTECH '16 (judged by a panel from industry and academia)
2009–Present	Graduate Research Fellow, Drexel University
2008-2009	Milton Rosenberg Scholar, Drexel University (recognizing outstanding engineering students)
2009	Senior Design Competition Winner, Drexel ECE (for a real-time RFID-based product locating system)
2006-2009	Dean's Scholarship Recipient, Drexel University
2008	Inductee, Eta Kappa Nu National ECE Honor Society

Academic Projects

NACHOS EDUCATIONAL OPERATING SYSTEM IMPLEMENTATION

Fall 2011

• Implemented in Java various features of a modern operating system: paging, virtual memory, locks and semaphores, conditional variables, and multi-threaded operations

FAST FOURIER TRANSFORM (FFT) PERFORMANCE BENCHMARKING ON CPU AND GPU

Winter 2011

Implemented and measured runtime performance of various FFT implementation in C and CUDA

MULTI-THREADED MATRIX OPERATIONS USING BLAS AND LAPACK

Winter 2011

 Wrote C programs to perform LU decomposition on large matrices, then parallelized the implementations using Pthreads, OpenMP, and Cilk

COMPILER CONSTRUCTION FOR SPL (SIGNAL PROCESSING LANGUAGE)

Spring 2010

 Constructed a scanner, parser, and interpreter for a Lisp-style language targeted for describing signal processing kernels called SPL, using Java Lex and Yacc

IMPLEMENTATION OF A 5-STAGE PIPELINED CPU ON FPGA

Winter 2010

• Implemented a 5-stage pipelined CPU supporting Load/Store, R-type instructions, branching, and context switches in VHDL. Performed FPGA synthesis and verification on the Xilinx Spartan 3E board

Other Activities

Journal and Conference Peer-Review

Philadelphia, PA

EXTERNAL REVIEWER

2012-Present

- Performed peer-review and provided publication recommendations for submitted manuscripts
- Journals: IEEE Trans. on Vehicular Techology, IEEE Trans. on Internet of Things
- Conferences: IEEE VTC '14 / '15, CROWNCOM '12

National Science Foundation (NSF) Research Grant Proposals

Drexel University

CONTRIBUTOR

2011-Present

- Performed literature survey, formulated research thrusts, and assisted the Principal Investigators (PIs) in writing grant proposals
- Awarded grants to Pls: CNS-1147838 (WiFiUS 2011), CNS-1422964 (NeTS-Small 2014), CNS-1457306 (WiFiUS 2014)

Local Professional Meetings and Conferences

Philadelphia, PA

STUDENT VOLUNTEER

2015-Present

Worked registration desk and monitored presentation & poster sessions at IEEE ISPASS '15, IEEE CNS '16

Local Political Convention (Democratic National Convention)

Philadelphia, PA

RADIO FREQUENCY (RF) COORDINATION VOLUNTEER

7/2016

· Handled the RF coordination procedure: static allocation of available spectrum to media organizations, device inspection and tagging, floor sweep to monitor spectrum usage, troubleshoot interference incidents. Details summarized in a technical report [T1]

IEEE Student Branch Drexel University

LOGISTICS CHAIR

2010

 Handled logistics operations in the organization: organize membership drives, book event venues, prepare refreshments and meeting materials, contact and schedule event speakers

GSA Education. Inc. Hanoi. Vietnam

FOUNDING MEMBER

2008

- Co-founded a professional education service company in Vietnam. Services include tutoring and college application consulting
- Led the development of the company's web portal for customer relationship management